## **ERIC MUTHOMI**

P.O Box 35625- 00100 Nairobi Tel: +254 712 194 827

Email: <u>muthomieric97@gmail.com</u>
LinkedIn: <u>www.linkedin.com/in/muthomieric</u>

### PROFILE SUMMARY

A Versatile Human Resource Professional with four **(4)** years' experience in managing and leading a wide range of Human Resource functions and strategic initiatives including Recruitment and Selection, Benefits Administration, Coordinating Training Programs, Performance Management, Workplace Health and Safety and Compliance. Skilled in Developing and Implementing HR Policies that promote a positive work environment, ensuring compliance with labour laws, ensuring employees well-being, addressing Human Resource related challenges/issues, HR Analytics and Reporting and enhancing HR processes to support business objectives for outstanding business results.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Teachers Service Commission (TSC)

Jan 2023-Present

Human Resource Officer- Marsabit, Kenya

- Verifying information relating to recruitment, appointment, transfers and salary payment
- Authorizing payroll data amendments, employees leave verifying and authorizing;
- Carrying out training needs assessment and preparing training proposals;
- Attending to general correspondence and responding to employees queries on HR issues;
- Capturing employee data on appointment, coding and promotion;
- Supervising and guiding employees for optimum performance.
- Implementing ICT related policies, guidelines, standards and procedures and providing end-user support

#### Persea Oils & Orchards Limited

Apr 2022-Dec 2022

Human Resource Assistant- Thika, Kenya

- Posting job vacancies on various platforms, screen applications, shortlist candidates for interviews, coordinate and schedule interviews with selected candidates, conducting preliminary interviews and providing feedback to candidates;
- Preparing and sending out employment offer letters and contracts;
- Facilitate new employee onboarding, including documentation and introduction to company policies and procedures;
- Identifying employee training needs and coordinating relevant training programs;
- Monitor employee performance and assist in performance appraisal processes;
- Handle routine HR inquiries from employees and provide support regarding HR policies and procedures;
- Preparing and ensuring that payment of statutory deductions (PAYEE, NSSF, NHIF, NITA) are duly made within reasonable time in collaboration with the accounts department
- Handling disciplinary matters and taking appropriate administrative action;

### Technical and Vocational Education and Training Authority (TVETA)

Apr 2021-Apr 2022

Human Resource and Administration Internship-Nairobi, Kenya

- Maintained accurate and up-to-date employee records, both in electronic and physical formats;
- Providing administrative support to the HR department, such as preparing correspondence, scheduling meetings, and filing documents;
- Processing documentation and prepare reports relating to personnel activities (staffing, recruitment, training, grievances, performance evaluations etc)
- Supporting in recruitment and selection of employees and preparing staff induction and on-boarding programs;
- Assisted the line's heads in administering performance appraisal, analysing and preparing related reports;
- Updating the HR Information Systems and generating accurate HR reports;

Aug 2023-Present

Dec 2020

Human Resource Attachment- Nairobi, Kenya

- Handle routine HR inquiries from employees and provide support;
- Prepare correspondences and forwarding them to actioning officer;
- Filing documents, updated incoming and outgoing employee personal files and records;
- Administered Training Needs Assessment tools and prepared training projections;
- Assisted in updating employee database;

Certified Human Resource Professional (PART III On-going)

### **EDUCATION**

Bachelor of Human Resource Management: Karatina University	Aug 2016-Mar 2021
Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education (KCSE) (B plain): Igoki Boys Secondary School	2012-2015
Kenya Certificate of Primary Education (KCPE): St Eugenia Primary School	2003-2011
OTHER PROFESSIONAL TRAINING AND CERTIFICATIONS	
Employment Contract Management Training (Atarah Solutions)	Aug 2024
Green Digital Skills Certificate (INCO Academy)	Feb 2024
Budget and Financial Reports Certificate (Pathways Solutions Services)	Jun 2023
Virtual Team Building and Management Certificate (Pathways Solutions Services)	Jun 2023
Improving Self Awareness Certificate (Pathways Solutions Services)	Jun 2023
Work Life Balance Certificate (Pathways Solutions Services)	Apr 2023
Master HR Training (Corporate Staffing Services)	May 2022
Google Data Analytics Course (COURSERA)	Sep 2021
Microsoft Office 2010 Certificate (ALISON)	Jan 2021
Data Entry and Management Certificate (AJIRA)	Jan 2021

## **ASSOCIATIONS AND AFFILIATIONS**

Building Your Leadership Skills Course (COURSERA)

Associate member of Institute of Human Resource Management (IHRM) Member No. (015997)

## PROFESSIONAL/SOFTWARE SKILLS

- Problem Solving Skills
- Excellent Communication Skills
- Leadership Skills
- Time Management skills
- HRIS Software proficiency

- Microsoft Office Suite (Word, Excel, Outlook, PowerPoint)
- Data Entry and Management
- Analytical Skills Using Spreadsheets and Excel, SQL In Databases, Data Visualization Skills

### **REFEREES**

Esther N. Mukiha- Assistant Director HRM & ADMIN Technical and Vocational Education and Training Authority

Tel: +254 725 799 352

Email: esther.mukiha@tveta.go.ke

James Mwangi Gichure- Deputy County Director

Teachers Service Commission (TSC)

Tel: +254 720 835 772

Email: jamesgichure@tsc.go.ke

David Macharia- Process Coordinator

Persea Oils & Orchards Ltd Tel: +254 721 156 259

Email: david.persea@gmail.com